Guide to the Myrick Freeman Papers, 1967-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Myrick Freeman papers 1970-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Freeman, Myrick
5 linear feet Extent: 3750 Items
Myrick Freeman III is the William D. Shipman Professor of Economics, Emeritus, at Bowdoin College, where he has worked since 1965. The Myrick Freeman papers date from approximately 1970 to 2010 and document Freeman's career as a prominent economist at Bowdoin College and senior fellow at Resources for the Future in Washington, D.C. The materials in the collection cover Freeman's consulting work, participation in conferences and workshops, writings, as well as testimony for the U.S. Congress and other government entities.
RL.00417
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Myrick Freeman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
Myrick Freeman III is the William D. Shipman Professor of Economics, Emeritus, at Bowdoin College, where he has worked since 1965. Freeman received a B.A. in Economics from Cornell in 1957 and a M.A. (1964) and Ph.D. (1965) from the University of Washington. Freeman specializes in economics of the environment and resources, benefit-cost and risk-benefit analysis, and public policy analysis and has served as a Senior Fellow at Resources for the Future in Washington, D.C., a member of the Environmental Protection Agency's's Committee on Valuing the Protection of Ecological Systems and Services, and the National Academy of Sciences Committee on Mortality Risk Reduction Benefits from Decreasing Tropospheric Ozone Exposure. Freeman is the author or co-author of eight books in addition to many articles, research reports, and book reviews. He has also prepared testimony for the U.S. Congress and state of Maine concerning the environment.
Collection Overview
The Myrick Freeman papers date from approximately 1970 to 2010 and document Freeman's career as a prominent economist at Bowdoin College and senior fellow at Resources for the Future in Washington, D.C. The materials in the collection cover Freeman's consulting work, participation in conferences and workshops, writings, as well as testimony for the U.S. Congress and other government entities.
The Conferences & Workshops series includes documents from events Freeman attended and led. There are a number of course planning materials and student reports from Freeman's participation in the Environmental Economics Program for South East Asia (EEPSEA), as well as materials from National Science Foundation workshops and notes and minutes from meetings of the Maine Department of Environmental Protection.
The Consulting series contains contracts for different consulting jobs. Many of these jobs were contracted to organizations by such as the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), the Canadian Ministry of Health, or the World Bank among others, which then employed Freeman as a consultant.
The Testimony series encompasses Freeman's preparatory notes, research materials, and printed testimony. Freeman's testimony was delivered at state courts, private hearings, and before the U.S. Senate Interior and Insular Affairs Committee.
The Correspondence series contains Freeman's correspondence with colleagues, contractors, and individuals with whom he collaborated on various pieces of writing.
The Writings series includes three subseries. Among these, the Papers subseries includes articles, book chapters, conference papers, and book manuscripts which express and interpret Freeman's research findings. The Reports subseries contains assessments Freeman prepared for various state and federal agencies. Finally, the Reviews subseries primarily encompasses Freeman's published reviews of articles and books. Occasionally, Freeman's responses to his colleagues' reviews of his own work are also included.
The Research series contains notes, research articles and papers, transparencies, and other materials which Freeman collected or produced in preparation for various research and consulting projects.
The Electronic Records series includes DVD's with files for Freeman's papers, teaching, correspondence, and participation in workshops.
Subject Headings
Freeman, A. Myrick, 1936-; Bowdoin College; United States. Environmental Protection Agency; National Academy of Sciences; Environmental policy -- Economic aspects; Pollution -- Economic aspects; Economists -- Correspondence
Contents of Collection
- Conferences and Workshops, 1970-2010, (Less than 1 box)
  This series includes a variety of documents from conferences and workshops Freeman attended and led. There are a number of course planning materials and student reports from Freeman's participation in the Environmental Economics Program for South East Asia (EEPSEA), as well as materials from National Science Foundation workshops and notes and minutes from meetings of the Maine Department of Environmental Protection.
  - Sabatier: NSF Workshop, 1978 (Box 1)
  - NAS (The National Science Academies)-BCA, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Simspon-Ecology/Environment Workshop, 1994 (Box 1)
  - National Ocean Economics Project (Box 1)
  - Acid Rain Conference, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Contingent Valuation Conference, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Conference on the Implications of Executive Order 12291 for Environmental Policy, 1982 (Box 1)
  - RFF-BCA Conference, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Wallenberg Symposium, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Brown Crutchfield Marine Research Conference, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Discounting & Life Cycle Analysis, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Natural Resources Council of Maine-Hydropower, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Glen Canyon Environmental Studies (GCES) Peer Review Committee Meeting, 1993 (Box 1)
  - OECD Workshop, 2004 (Box 1)
  - MIT Workshop, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Measuring the Full Social Costs and Benefits of Transportation Conference, 1995 (Box 1)
  - GCES Non-Market Economics Workshop, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Maine Dept. of Environmental Protection Meeting, 1995 (Box 1)
  - New York Regulation Reform Roundtable, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Smithsonian Institution: Ecology and Economics Seminar Series, 1995 (Box 1)
  - External Costs of Energy Workshop: Brussels, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Economic Analysis and Environmental Decision-Making Conference, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Environmental Protection (EPA), Council of Economic Advisors and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Workshop, 196 (Box 1)
  - Philippine Environmental and Natural Resources Accounting Project (ENRAP) Training Workshop, 1998 (Box 1)
  - EPA Cincinnati Course, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Valuing Health Outcomes Conference, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Earth Day Seminar, 2003 (Box 1)
  - iHEA Conference, 2003 (Box 1)
  - South Africa Course: Economics of the Environment, 2003 (Box 1)
  - ENRAP Lectures, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Environmental Economics Program for South East Asia (EEPSEA) Course, 1997 (Box 1)
  - EEPSEA Course, 1998 (Box 1)
  - EEPSEA Course, 1999 (Box 1)
  - EEPSEA Course, 2000 (Box 1)
  - EEPSEA Course, 2002 (Box 1)
  - EEPSEA Course, 2004 (Box 1)
  - EEPSA Advisory Committee, 2005 (Box 1)
- Testimony, 1972-1994, (Less than 1 box)
  The Testimony series contains Freeman's preparatory notes, research materials (newspaper clippings, laws), and printed testimony delivered at deliberations and hearings regarding topics such as the Basin Mills Hydroelectric Power Development project, the Kenetech Windpower initiative, and the Trans-Alaska pipeline. Freeman's testimony was delivered at state courts in Maine (Natural Resources Council of Maine), private hearings, and before the U.S. Senate Interior and Insular Affairs Committee.
  - Economic and Environmental Effects: The Basin Mills Hydroelectric Power Development, 1992 (Box 1)
  - State of Maine Land Use Regulation Commission: Kenetech Windpower, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Trans-Alaska Pipeline Hearings, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Analysis of the Economic and Security Aspects of the Trans-Alaska Pipeline, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Hazardous Air Pollutants Regulations, National Resources Council of Maine (NRCM), 1984 (Box 1)
- Consulting, 1979-2004, (Less than 1 box)
  The Consulting series includes contracts for Freeman's different consulting jobs. Many of these jobs were contracted to organizations by such as the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), the Canadian Ministry of Health, or the World Bank among others, which then employed Freeman as an economics consultant to complete the proposed projects.
  - Stratus Consulting & EPA: Children's Health Valuation Handbook (Box 1)
  - World Bank: South Asia Sector Units (SAS) (Box 1)
  - Canadian Ministry of Health, Economic Analysis and Evaluation Division, 2001 (Box 1)
  - State of New York Office of the Attorney General, Natural Resources & Public Health Economics, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Trade and Industrial Policy Strategies (TIPS), 2003 (Box 1)
  - Industrial Economics, Inc. (IE): Valuing Fatal Risk, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Industrial Economics, Inc. (IE): United Nations Compensation Commission -Kuwait Oil Damages, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Industrial Economics, Inc. (IE): Health Effects (Box 1)
  - Southern Appalachian Mountain Initiative (SAMI) (Box 1)
  - Florida Dept. of Environmental Protection: National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Tampa Bay Oil Spill, 1997 (Box 1)
  - National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program: Economic Valuation of Acid Deposition Injury to Cultural Resources, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Glen Canyon Non-Use Study, 1994 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Office of Technology Assessment: Determining the Carcinogenic Risk from the Environment, 1979 (Box 1)
  - EPA: Water/RIA's, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Land Economics Editorial Board, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Southern Appalachian Mountain Initiative (SAMI) (Box 1)
  - Various Consulting Agreements & Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Emails RE: OMB, 2003 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1972-1994, (Less than 1 box)
  This series contains Freeman's correspondence with colleagues, contractors, and individuals with whom he collaborated on various pieces of writing.
  - Bromley: National Resource Economics: Policy Problems and Contemporary Analysis, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Letters: July 1, 1995-June 30, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Letters: July 1, 1996-June 30, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Letters: July 1, 1997-June 30, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Letters: July 1, 1998-June 30, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Letters: July 1, 1999-December, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Letters: January 1, 2001-December 12, 2002 (Box 2)
  - The National Science Academies: Ozone Mortality Risk Reduction Benefits from Decreasing Topospheric Ozone Exposure, 2008: Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Krutilla Research Award Correspondence, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Vig & Kraft, Ed.: Environmental Policy, Fifth Edition Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Resources for the Future (RFF) Fundraising Campaign, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Krutilla Research Award Correspondence, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Emails regarding SANDEE, 2006 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1967-2000, (2 boxes)
  The Writing series contains two subseries: Papers and Reviews. The Papers subseries includes drafts, notes, and published versions of papers which Freeman delivered at conferences or published for various journals, edited volumes, and institutions (Maine Audubon Society, or Resources for the Future, for example). There are also papers which were influential for Freeman. The Reviews subseries contains These materials are listed by the name of the publication, title, and date, where this information is available.
  - Papers
    The Papers subseries includes Freeman's articles, book chapters, conference papers, and book manuscripts which express and interpret his research findings.
    - National Science Academies: Polychlorinated Biphenyls (PCBs) (Box 2)
    - The American Economics Association: Approaches to Measuring Public Goods Demands (Box 2)
    - Scandanavian Journal of Economics: Hedonic Prices, Property Values and Measuring Environmental Benefits: A Survey of the Issues, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Land Economics: Comment on Mark Plummer's The Sign and Size of Option Value, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Festschrift honoring James Crutchfield: Uncertainty and Option Value in Environmental Policy, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Association of Environmental and Resource Economists (AERE): Uncertainty and Environmental Policy: The Role of Option and Quasi-Option Values, 1984 (Box 2)
    - AERE Newsletter: Natural Resources Damage Assessment under CERCLA (Compensation and Liability Act of 1980), 1986 (Box 2)
    - Public Policies for Environmental Protection, RFF: "Water Pollution Policy," 1985 (Box 2)
    - Futures: Taiwan 2000 Study, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Handbook of Natural Resource and Energy Economics, Kneese and Sweeney, Ed.: Methods for Assessing the Benefits of Environmental Programs, 1985 (Box 2)
    - National Science Foundation (NSF) & Arthur D. Little (ADL): Evaluation of the State-of-the-Art in Benefits Methods for Public Policy Purposes, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Advances in Applied Microeconomics, Smith Ed.: Methodology for Economic Impact Analysis of Climate Change, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Environmental Economics and Management: Depletable Externalities and Pigouvian Taxation, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Land Economics: Supply Uncertainty, Option Price, and Option Value, 1985 (Box 2)
    - American Association for Retired Persons (AARP) Public Policy Institute: Exploring the Role of Cost-Benefit Analysis in Government Regulations, 2003-2007 (Box 2)
    - Comments on Advanced Notice of Proposed Rulemaking Regulations for Type B Natural Resource Damage Assessment Regulations, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Policy in the 1990's, 2nd Ed., Vig and Kraft, Ed., 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Policy in the 1990's, 3rd Ed., Kraft and Vig, Ed.: Economics, Incentives, and Environmental Regulation, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Policy in the 1990's, 4th Ed., Kraft and Vig, Ed.: Economics, Incentives, and Environmental Regulation, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Science Technology: On Measuring Economic Values for Nature, 2000 (Box 2)
    - A Companion to Environmental Philosophy, Jamieson, Ed.: Economic Valuation, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Regulation: Misrepresenting ACCACA, 2001 (Box 2)
    - The Bowdoin Orient: Global Warming, President Bush, and Kyoto: 2001 (Box 2)
    - Agricultural and Resource Economics Review: Environmental Policy Since Earth Day I: What Do We Know About the Benefits and Costs?, 2001 (Box 2)
    - The Bowdoin Orient and Southwest Hydrology: Arsenic in Drinking Water: How Much is Too Much?, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Economic Perspectives: Environmental Policy since Earth Day I: What Have We Gainted?, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Unpublished: Equity, Feasibility, and the Volunteer Army, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Unpublished: The Relevance of Benefit-Cost Analysis: A Comment on Exchange, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Unpublished: Upward Bound: A Benefit-Cost Analysis, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Unpublished: The Publication Lag, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Material for a Report on the Environment, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Social Report: An Overview of the Environment, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation of Idarado Damage Claim from CVM-Shea & Gardner Natural Resource Damage Case, Colorado, 1988 (Box 2)
    - The Resources for the Future Reader in Environmental and Resource Management: Assessing Damages from the Valdez Oil Spill, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Maine Audubon Society: Values Bibliography, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Bowdoin College Economics Working Paper Series: Calculating the Social Cost of Electricity When the Rate of Return on Capital and Individuals' Rates of Time Preference Are Different, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Androscoggin Greenways, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Marine Resource Economics: The Benefits of Water Quality Improvements for Marine Recreation: A Review of the Empirical Evidence, 1995 (Box 2)
    - A Workshop on the Economic and Environmental Valuation of Coastal and Estuarine Resources Book, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF) & The Social Costing Debate: Issues and Resolutions, 1992 (Box 2)
    - The Journal of the International Society for Ecological Economics: Valuing Environmental Resources under Alternative Management Regimes, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Response to Joskow's "Let's Do it Right" Paper, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Southern Economic Journal: Welfare Measurement and the Benefit-Cost Analysis of Projects Affecting Risks, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Journal of Risk and Uncertainty: Indirect Methods for Valuing Changes in Environmental Risks with Nonexpected Utility Preferences, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Krutilla Festschrif Volume, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Association of Environmental and Resource Economists and American Economic Association: Assessing Damages to Marine Resources: PCBs in New Bedford Harbor, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Risk Analysis: Ex Ante and Ex Post Values for Changes in Risks, 1989 (Box 3)
    - A Short Note on Irreversibility and Benefit-Cost Tests, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Introduction: Economic and Political Issues in Risk Analysis, 1989 (Box 3)
    - The Wall Street Journal: Exxon Valdez: You Can Put a Price on Scenic Beauty, 1989 (Box 3)
    - The Environment and Natural Resources Division, Congressional Research Service: Health Benefits of Controlling Air Pollution: An Economic Perspective & Estimating Individuals' Values for Health Benefits, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF): Nonuse Values in Natural Resource Damage Assessment, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF): Economics Clarifies Choices about Managing Risk, 1989 (Box 3)
    - American Economics Association Meeting & American Association for the Advancement of Science Meeting: Economics and the Rational Management of Risk, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Measuring the Demand for Environmental Quality, Braden and Kolstad, Ed.:Health, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Southern Economic Journal: Measuring Welfare Values of Productivity Changes, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF): The Hedonic Price Approach to Measuring Demand for Neighborhood Characteristics, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Futures: Equity, Efficiency, and Discounting. The Reasons for Discounting Intergenerational Effects, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Public Economics: Congestion, Quality Deterioration, and Heterogeneous Tastes, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Council on Environmental Quality: Some Issues in the Estimation and Use of Benefit Measures, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF): The State of Benefit Analysis of Environmental Regulation (Box 3)
    - Journal of Environmental Economics and Management: Some Extensions of a Simple Value of Life-Saving Model, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Benefits of Pollution Control: Review and Synthesis, 1980 (Box 3)
    - American Economic Association Meeting: Measuring Benefits from Air Pollution Control: Where Do We Stand?, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Resources for the Future (RFF): Reform of Environmental Regulation, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Maine Audubon Society: Wells Harbor Dredging Controversy, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Natural Resources Council of Maine: Economics-Nuclear Referendum, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Environmental Policy: Benefits of Air Pollution Control Overview, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Land Economics: The Sign and Size of Option Value, 1984 (Box 3)
    - The National Ocean Economics Program: Towards the Development of a Marine Non-Market Values Information System, 2005 (Box 3)
    - Handbook of Environmental Economics, Maler and Vincent, Ed.: Welfare Theory and Valuation, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Water Resources Research: Technology-Based Effluent Standards: The U.S. Case, 1980 (Box 3)
    - The Full Costs and Benefits of Transportation, Greene, Jones, and Delucchi, Ed.: Externalities, Prices and Taxes: Second Best Issues in Transportation, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Resource and Energy Economics: Estimating the Environmental Costs of Electricity: An Overview and Review of the Issues, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Environmental and Resource Economics: Valuing Environmental Health Effects-An Economic Perspective, 2006 (Box 3)
    - Political Economy Research (PERC): Counting the Wealth of Nature: An Overview of Ecosystem Valuation, 2005-2007 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Environmental Economics and Management: Some Simple Analytics of Social Costing in a Regulated Industry, 1993 (Box 3)
    - The Electricity Journal: Ranking Electric Generating Technologies with External Costs, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Bowdoin College Economics Working Paper Series: The Environmental Cost of Electricity: An Exercise in Pricing the Environment, 1995 (Box 3)
    - A Primer on Nonmarket Valuation, Brown, Boyle, & Champ, Ed.: Economic Valuation: What and Why, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Economic Analysis and Evaluation & AERE Newsletter: On Quality Adjusted Life Years (QALYs) and Environmental/Consumer Safety Valuation, 2002 (Box 3)
    - The Economic Analysis and Evaluation Division (EAED) of the Healthy Environments and Consumer Safety Branch, Health Canada: On Discounting Lives, 2001 (Box 3)
    - The Economic Analysis and Evaluation Division (EAED) of the Healthy Environments and Consumer Safety Branch, Health Canada: On Cost-Utility Analysis, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Chapters for Handbook of Environmental Economics, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    The Reports subseries contains assessments which Freeman prepared for various state and federal agencies, such as Maine and New York State's EPA, or the U.S. Congress's Committee on Energy and Commerce.
    - The Clean Air Task Force: The Benefits of Environmental Comparability in New York State, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Science: Letter to Science RE: Old Cars and Taxation, 1989 (Box 3)
    - The Morris Colloquium "Environmental Policy: Ethics and Economics"L The Ethical Basis of Economic View of the Environment, 1982 (Box 3)
    - The Benefits and Costs of the Dickey-Lincoln Project: A Preliminart Report, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Glen Canyon Non-Use Value Study, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Electric Power Research Institute (EPRI): Technical Review of Externality Issues, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Maine Economists Question Rationale Behind Turnpike Widening, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Energy and Commerce, U.S. House of Representatives: The Costs and Benefits of Smoking Restrictions: An Assessment of the Smoke-Free Environment Act of 1993 (Box 3)
  - Reviews
    The Reviews subseries primarily includes Freeman's published reviews of articles and books by other economists. Occasionally, Freeman's responses to his colleagues' reviews of his own work are also included.
    - Environment Canada: Review of Current Evaluation of Environmental Reference Inventory (EVRI) System Review, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Department of Environmental Protection/NOAA: Tampa Bay Spills, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Natural Resources Forum: Review of David Pearce, Evaluating Uncertainty: Economic Values and the Natural World, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Review of Mary Jo Kealy, The Economic Value of Mid and South Atlantic Sportfishing, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Review of Mary Jo Kealy, the Benefits of Clean Water Chapter, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Review of Research Triangle Park, The Benefits of Diversionary Users of Improved Water Quality: Phase I Assessment, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Review of Ground Water Benefits Framework, 1995 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census: National Survey of Fishing, Hunting, and Wildlife-Associated Recreation, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Review of Paul Scodari, Revised Wetlands Benefits Report, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Review of Dennis M. King, Wetland Creation and Restoration: An Integrated Framework for Evaluating Costs, Expected Results and Compensation Ratios, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Benefits Taxonomy, 1991 (Box 3)